What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that medical journals
can cost tens of thousands per year
for a subscription and even
access to a single online article
can cost dozens of dollars.
But the founder of
the website Sci-Hub,
a woman known as
“The Robin Hood of Science”,
set out to change that.
Here’s her story.
The first issues of the first scientific
journals were published back in 1665,
in which it was noted things like, hey,
it looks like there's a spot on Jupiter,
thanks to new telescopes
invented by a certain Mr. Newton,
whose friend Halley described a comet.
The same journal that reported that
oranges and lemons could cure scurvy,
and something in willow tree
bark could bring down a fever.
Also published, a letter by
some guy over in the colonies
about playing with kites
during lightning storms,
and an account of a remarkable 8-year-old
musician by the name of Amadeus,
and within this last century some
sketchings of the structure
of some molecule called DNA.
A journal still in publication
to this day, 350 years later,
available now online and in print
for the low, low subscription
price of only $6,666 a year.
As you can imagine, the
high price of journals
leaves doctors in developing countries
missing out on relevant
information about health.
At that time, back in the '90s, there
was optimism that by 2004 at least,
the problem of access to life-saving
scientific information would be solved.
But 2004 came and went,
setting their sights for 2015.
Surely by then we can achieve
health information for all,
as lack of access
remained a major barrier.
Realistically, only scientists at really
big, well-funded universities
in the developed world may have
full access to published research,
and as prices rise even higher,
even that may no longer be true.
You know there's a problem
when even Harvard,
as in $30-billion-dollar-
endowment Harvard,
claims that costs for research
journals are now prohibitive.
Meanwhile, the journal
publishers are raking in billions
charging institutions up to
$35,000 a year per journal,
and charging individuals
online per article.
So you have a family member diagnosed
with some disease and you go online.
You can read all sorts of internet drek,
but if you want to see the actual
science, it can get expensive.
And you likely paid for the research.
Tax dollars pour in to fund the research,
and then you can't get access
to the research you paid for.
It's like if a nice little city park was built,
but then some private firm came in
and started to charge admission.
That's roughly how it works
with scientific research,
and this conversion of public research
dollars into private publishing profits
has long been a source of discontent.
The publishers don't end up
paying anything for the research.
They get it for free; they don't
pay the researchers anything.
So we pay for it, and then we have
to pay for it again if we want to read it.
So it can end up with science as a profit
system, rather than science as knowledge.
Enter Alexandra Elbakyan, nicknamed
by some the Robin Hood of Science.
It's the story of how one researcher made
nearly every scientific paper ever published
available for free to everyone,
anywhere in the world.
Named by perhaps the most prestigious
scientific journal in the world
as one of the top 10 people who
mattered the most in science in 2016,
Alexandra started out as just a
frustrated grad student in Kazakhstan,
unable to access the scholarly papers
she needed for her research.
Once she figured out how to
circumvent all the paywalls,
she started a website,
now at https://sci-hub.st/
to remove all barriers
in the way of science
by giving away the world's scientific,
medical, and nutrition literature for free.
"What she did is nothing short
of awesome," said one researcher.
"Lack of access to the scientific
literature is a massive injustice,
and she fixed it with one fell swoop."
Alexandra Elbakyan, a 20-
something year old grad student,
is operating a free searchable
online database
of nearly 50 million stolen
scholarly journal articles,
shattering the $10 billion-per-year
paywall of academic publishers,
an awe-inspiring act of altruism,
or a massive criminal enterprise,
depending on whom you ask.
Now up to 60 million papers, providing
access to nearly all scholarly literature.
Via its websites sci-hub.cc,
sci-hub.io, and sci-hub.ac,
Sci-Hub was able to fill 99.3%
of articles requests, all for free.
A sister site, Library Genesis, at libgen.io,
distributes scientific books and textbooks
for free, more than a million
of them, also illegally.
Who's downloading pirated papers?
Everyone, concluded this feature
in the prestigious journal, Science.
A survey of potential users suggests for most
it's not some grand political statement,
but rather that's the only
way they have access,
or feel it's just so much quicker and easier.
Even those who have legitimate institutional
access may still choose to use Sci-Hub
because there's just so many
fewer hoops to jump through.
So you can imagine how
sites like Sci-Hub may
be filling publishers that charge for access
with roaring, existential panic,
and they're not taking it lying down.
Elsevier, the largest publisher, notorious
for demanding researchers take down
free copies of their own work,
sued Sci-Hub, the Library
Genesis project, Alexandra,
and 99 John Does for copyright infringement,
a willful disregard of Elsevier's rights.
Kind of hard to take the
moral high ground, though,
when you're effectively an
international arms dealer.
Can you imagine a tobacco
company publishing health journals?
Surely the company's business mission
would be impossibly confused:
would the company be in the business
of killing people or keeping them alive?
But if you can't imagine that absurdity,
well, welcome to Elsevier,
which in addition to
publishing medical journals
is also involved in the global arms trade,
running arms fairs where things
like cluster bombs are sold,
leading to medical journal editorial
boards calling for a boycott
of Elsevier's warmongering, health
damaging business practices.
In response to the lawsuit,
Alexandra wrote a letter to the judge.
She wanted to make it clear that not only
did Elsevier not create those papers,
but that they don't pay researchers a penny.
So it's not like pirated movie or song
where the content creator is losing out,
noting that no researcher had ever complained
that she was handing out their research.
In fact, scientific authors
are typically thrilled
when their work gets more
out into the world.
That's the whole point of science:
to be shared and built upon.
In one fell swoop,
Alexandra created a portal
likely offering a greater level
of access to science
than any institution on Earth in history,
literally opening up a world of knowledge.
And she's not backing down,
citing in her defense Article 27
of the United Nations Universal
Declaration of Human Rights,
that everyone should have the right to
freely participate in the cultural life
of the community, including sharing in
scientific advancement and its benefits.
She realizes she could be arrested and
extradited to the U.S. to face charges.
She is fully aware that another
computer prodigy-turned-advocate,
Aaron Swartz, was arrested on similar charges
after mass downloading academic papers.
Facing devastating financial penalties
and jail time, Swartz hanged himself.
Note: since I recorded the
narration for that episode,
Sci-Hub.io was shut down,
but the site can currently
be reached at sci-hub.st.
It can also be reached at five other domains
should that one get yanked, too.
You can always see the
updated active link list
on the Sci-Hub Wikipedia page.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.